Student Strike of 1970 Files, 1968-1971
Smith College Archives
Student Strike of 1970 Files
1968-1971
Smith College.
RG 80 UUID:1c192289-70f7-4a75-aac0-c9185b6585c8
3 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Student anti-war demonstration. Contains correspondence, diaries, notes, speeches, notices, posters, memoranda, photographs, petitions, newsletters, packets, press releases and newspaper clippings
The idea of a nationally coordinated student strike developed over a period of at least two years of growing tension between the federal administration and minority and student groups who expressed dissatisfaction with the undeclared war in Vietnam, the military draft, and economic consequences of the war. Coordinated by the National Moratorium Committee (organized in June 1969), Moratorium Days held on October 15, 1969 and November 15, 1969 included the suspension of classes, neighborhood canvassing, protest marches and petitions. The third week in March 1970 was proclaimed National Anti-Draft Week. Planned demonstrations were held at local draft board offices, and "we won't go" petitions were circulated. In 1970, the Fast for Peace was held on April 13, 14, and 15, as an expression of moral concern about the war. In early May, student opposition intensified with the knowledge of the expansion of the conflict into Cambodia, President Nixon's April 3 announcement of his decision to resume bombing in North Vietnam, and the treatment of dissenters in the United States. On May 4, the day of the killings on the Kent State University campus, "leaders of the National Student Association and the former Vietnam Moratorium Committee officially called for a nationwide strike of indefinite duration" (Facts on File 1970, p.299).
At Smith, the Moratorium Days were occasions for student involvement in the local community. Smith students staffed the Green Street Moratorium office, canvassed residents, and coordinated marches down Main Street with the cooperation of local businesses. The first Moratorium Day was October 15, 1969 and was called Work for Peace Day at Smith. Smith's Chaplain the Rev. Richard P. Unsworth participated in a memorial service for Hampshire County veterans held at the Unitarian Church. On the second Moratorium Day, November 15, 1969, a contingent of 250 Smith students and 10 Smith professors attended the march in Washington, D. C to protest the Vietnam War. In Northampton, the weekend of November 15 included a teach-in at Wright Hall, a silent march from Helen Hills Hills Chapel to the center of Northampton and back, and well-attended coffee klatches held in a number of Northampton homes.
A timeline of activities at Smith during the May, 1970 Strike is provided below. During and after the strike, alumnae and friends of the college became involved. On May 30, President Mendenhall announced that his office was receiving 10 letters a day expressing opinions about the strike (tape recording of last Chapel,../../70). Many seminars were repeated during Commencement Weekend for the benefit of alumnae and parents, and a video tape of many of the strike activities was shown. The following organizations formed at Smith due to the strike: the Strike Committee, the Education Committee, the Community Action Committee, Union for National Draft Opposition, Committee on Justice and Repression at Home, Unofficial Committee of Concerned Citizens, Committee on Governance, and the People's Lobby. The activities of the People's Lobby continued beyond the academic year, with students working in Northampton, in Washington D. C., and in their hometown to spread information and coordinate lobbying efforts. Several existing Smith organizations took part in Strike activities; these include: the Student Government Association, the Committee on Educational Policy, the Faculty - Student Committee, and the Young Republican Club.
May 4, 5 p.m. At regularly scheduled all-college meetings, a few students and a professor speak about strike issues, and there is a discussion of race/foreign policy distinction.
May 4, 8 p.m. About 30 people opposed to the strike gather in front of Neilson Library. Meanwhile at Paradise pond, Professor Donald Robinson offers a plan for lobbying Congress.
May 5 About 300 students rally at Davis to hear speeches against U. S. action in Cambodia and in support of Bobby Seale. Smith students vote to strike, 1547 to 437 (12 abstentions). Smith faculty vote to suspend all normal college activities from May 6 to May 10.
May 5,ca. 11 p.m. In response to a controversy over whether President Mendenhall had announced the results of the student strike vote at the faculty meeting, students and professors stand outside the President's house in the rain until it is announced that there was a failure of communication and that a faculty meeting will be held the next day.
May 6 At an all-college meeting, the Sid Waller '70 speech and the BSA speech, both contained in this collection, are delivered.
May 7, 4 p.m. The Government Department sponsors a lecture at the J. M. Greene Hall on President Nixon's policy in Cambodia.
May 7,5 p.m. A student statement of purpose is read to 15 area clergy and 40 Smith students at a meeting in the Helen Hills Hills Chapel lounge led by the Rev. Richard P. Unsworth and Rabbi Yechiael Lander.
May 8, 9 a.m. A memorial service is held in the Helen Hills Hills Chapel for the Kent State dead.
May 9 Smith students attend a protest march in Washington, D.C.
May 10 Students from Smith and other area colleges canvass local residents. Black Panther Doug Miranda lectures in the Quad to a group of about 300 people.
May 31 Commencement exercises bring the Student Strike at Smith College to a close; however, many organizations and students remained active throughout the summer.
The approximately one linear foot of files relating to the Student Strike of 1970 consist of a variety of materials including correspondence, diaries, notes, speeches, notices, posters, memoranda, photographs, petitions, newsletters, packets, press releases and newspaper clippings.
Although the collection spans March 11, 1968 - March 19, 1971, most of the material dates from mid April to early June, 1970. This collection provides material from a wide variety of sources representing different view points concerning the Student Strike of 1970. The material specific to Smith College includes first person accounts, such as notes, diaries, and correspondence in addition to newsletters, packets, and statements.
Of particular interest are the correspondence of Sien-Nyat Chin '73; the diaries of Lucy Bodine '72, and Sarah Gordon '72 and student speeches. Also of interest are the material from faculty and staff, such as the correspondence and notes of Michele Aldrich, an exam of Charles Melvin, memoranda from President Mendenhall, and a petition drafted by Cecilia Marie Kenyon. Organizations mentioned in the SMITH - General series include the Unofficial Committee of Concerned Citizens, the Committee on Governance, the Student Government Association, the Committee on Educational Policy, the Faculty - Student Committee, and the Young Republican Club.
The collection also shows how the Student Strike of 1970 at Smith was organized and structured to include educational programs, lobbying, economic boycotts, and community action programs. The effort was to make an impact on both local and national levels.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Smith
II. Other Colleges
III. Newsclippings
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
This collection documenting the Strike of 1970 is open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
In the Spring 1985, the College Archives received a collection of files relating to the strike of 1970. The material had been collected by Sarah Gordon '72 and David Allmendinger, Assistant Professor of History. The papers themselves describe the process of collecting examples of notices circulating during the strike (see Sarah Gordon's diary), and include evidence that Prof. Allmendinger solicited further contributions after the strike was over. This collection was merged with a few College Archives files from the strike of 1970. Many of the newsclippings may have been collected by the Smith News Office.
Search Terms
Smith College--Strike, 1970.; Student strikes--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975--Protest movements--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Smith College.
Additional Information
Related Material
Other sources of information related to the strike of 1970 include the Sophian, beginning with November 1968 and including April 13 - April 20, 1978; the Smith Alumnae Quarterly, especially August 1970; The Report of the President 1969-70; and a tape of Last Chapel, May 29, 1970, with remarks by President Mendenhall. The Smith Centennial Study oral History project (12. Anniversaries) includes interviews with a few alumnae who were students during the strike. The Class of 1970 commencement folder (80. Class 1970) may be of use as well.
- SERIES I. SMITH March 11, 1968 - March 1971, undated, .5 linear feet
  The first and largest subseries, SMITH - General, contains material originating from individuals and administrative offices, as well as material of unknown origin.
  The hierarchy of Smith College is ignored, and this series is divided into nine of the special committees that were active during the strike. The subseries include: General, Canvass Committee; Economic Boycott Committee; Education Committee; People's Lobby; Committee on Political Repression at Home; Strike Committee; Union for National Draft Opposition; and William Allan Neilson Library.
  - General
    - Correspondence
      - General May 11 - Jun 6, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Aldrich, Michele May 4 - 20, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Alumnae Mar 11, 1968 - May 20, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - United States Congress May 7 - Jul 7, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Enclosures Oct 31, 1969 - Jun 5, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Diaries
      - Bodine, Lucy '72 May 8 - 16, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Gordon, Sarah '72 May 3 - 10, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Directories undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Exams May 30, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Fact sheets c. May 9, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Memorabilia undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Memoranda
      - General May 12, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Faculty and staff Apr 17 - Jun 1, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - President Mendenhall May 14 - 19, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Registrar, Office of May 7 - 11, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Treasurer, Office of May 11, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Newsletters May 4 - 5, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Notes of meetings
      - General May 5, 9, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Aldrich, Michele undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Notices, posters Feb 20 - Jun 1, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Petitions May, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Photographs Spring 1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Press releases and letters to editor May, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Reports May 12, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Speeches May 4 - 31, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Statements
      - Faculty and staff May 5 - 12, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Students May 10, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Strike votes, ballots May 5, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Subjects
      - Memorial Service May 8, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Questionnaires May 15, 1970, Mar 19, 1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Canvass Committee
    - Canvasser's packet May 10, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Economic Boycott Committee
    - Notices, statements, report undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Education Committee
    - Memoranda c. May 8, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Schedules May 12 - 18, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Seminars
      - General
        - - notes May 8, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
        - -notices, schedules, reading lists May 7 - 18, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Guidelines for Community Action May, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - The Role of Science in American Democracy c. May 8 - 20, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - The Smith Strike as History May 9, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - People's Lobby
    - Correspondence May 7 - 29, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Directory c. May 13, 1970, May 8, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Information
      - about correspondence with Congress May 6 - 8, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - general, statements of purpose c. May 6, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Newsletter Jun 16 - Sept 8, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Packets
      - Introductory packet and policy statement May 9 - 13, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
      - Alumnae packet early May, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - Legislative research information sheets undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Packet sent to other schools May 12, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - Washington packet lobbying May 11 - 13, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - First packet to state captains late May, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - June 1 packet Jun 1, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - June 17 packet Jun 17, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - July 3 packet Jul 3, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - August 21 packet Aug 21, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Photographs undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Press releases and letters to editors May 9, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Political Repression at Home, Committee on
    - Fact sheet undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Strike Committee
    - Directory c. May 7, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Memoranda May 3 - 8, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Office messages May 9, 1970, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Newsletters May 4 - 31, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Schedules May 5 - 31, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Union for National Draft Opposition c. May 8 - 13, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - William Allan Neilson Library
    - Bibliographies May 7, 8, 21, 1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
- SERIES II. OTHER COLLEGES February - June 19, 1970, undated, .25 linear feet
  This series is divided into Local and National subseries.
  The Local subseries consists of material from Amherst College, Hampshire College, Mt. Holyoke College, and University of Massachusetts. This subseries also includes material from organizations affiliated with the five colleges and other local organizations.
  The National subseries includes material from Dartmouth College and Yale University, as well as from various other colleges in the U. S. In addition, it includes a letter from the American Council on Education regarding tax exemption and political activities at colleges.
  - Local
    - 5-College Communications Center
      - Newsletter May 8 - 10, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 65)
      - Memorandum, petition, report May 13 - 15, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 66)
      - Schedules May 7 - 16, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Amherst College May 4 - 8, 1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Hampshire College May 7 - 13, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Mt. Holyoke College May 7 - 25, 1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - University of Massachusetts Mar 3 - May 17, 1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Valley Peace Center newsletter May 9 - 14, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Other organizations c. May 1970 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - National
    - American Council on Education Jun 19, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Dartmouth College May 6 - 27, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Yale University Apr 19 - May 18, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Other institutions Febr - Jun 13, 1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
- SERIES III. NEWSCLIPPINGS May 6 - September 29, 1970. undated, 1 folder
  This series contains newsclippings pertaining to Smith College and the other area colleges. There are also national newclippings relating to the nationwide Student Strike of 1970.
  - Various May 6 - Sept 29, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 78)